# Joel A. Masselink

Residing in: Seattle, Washington phone: +1 (774) 232-7629 website: <a href="mailto:www.joelmasselink.com">www.joelmasselink.com</a> e-mail: <a href="mailto:jmasselink@gmail.com">jmasselink@gmail.com</a>

#### INTRODUCTION

Joel Masselink is a geospatial consultant with over 10 years of experience in designing maps, curating datasets, and conducting analyses in support of conservation, development, and environmental projects. Joel is currently seeking a role which uses his problem-solving experience and geospatial science skillset.

## **EDUCATION**

Clark University MA, Geographic Information Science

Worcester, MA; 2009

Coursework: geospatial databases, remote sensing, environmental & land change modeling

James Madison University BS, Geographic Science

Harrisonburg, VA; 2005

Coursework: GIS, spatial analysis, spatial statistics, image processing; minor in History.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# Earth Logic, LLC Principal Consultant

Seattle, WA; 2014 – 2015, 2018 - present

• Providing custom geospatial solutions for clients in the environmental, natural resources, and international development sectors.

#### **SELECT CONSULTANCIES**

- Great Elephant Census Forest Initiative Data Analysis. Consultancy with Wildlife Conservation Society.
- · Spatial Data Assessment of Large-Scale Infrastructure in the Lower Mekong Region. Consultancy with Wildlife Conservation Society.
- · Standardizing Large Mammal Surveys to the SMART-Ecological Records Data Model for Central Africa. Consultancy with World Resources Institute.
- Cartography of DRC Protected Area network. Consultancy with World Wildlife Fund / PARAP (Protected Area System Assessment in the Democratic Republic of Congo).

# Vulcan, Inc. GIS Developer, Impact Engineering

Seattle, WA; 2015 – 2018

- · Contributed geospatial data processing and visualization to software engineering projects.
- · Provided data quality assurance, management, and mapping for large-scale wildlife surveys.

#### Wildlife Conservation Society GIS Coordinator

Democratic Republic of Congo; 2009 – 2013

- · Built GIS capacity through training, mentoring, and project management.
- · Managed and analyzed spatial data for land-use planning and wildlife monitoring activities.
- · Conducted land-cover mapping, land-change assessment, and species distribution modeling.

# USAID Africa Bureau Intern, CARPE

Democratic Republic of Congo; 2008

· Designed landscape maps for Congo Basin Forest Partnership publication, State of the Forest 2008.

## NAEVA Geophysics GIS Specialist / Database Manager

Charlottesville, VA; 2006 – 2007

· Managed target databases and provided GIS support for geophysical surveying projects.

# Joel A. Masselink

Residing in: Seattle, Washington phone: +1 (774) 232-7629 website: <a href="mailto:www.joelmasselink.com">www.joelmasselink.com</a> e-mail: <a href="mailto:jmasselink@gmail.com">jmasselink@gmail.com</a>

## SKILL SUMMARY

- · Geoprocessing using GDAL/OGR commands, Python, ArcPy, and ModelBuilder
- · Familiarity with authoritative public domain and open geospatial datasets (OpenStreetMap)
- · Geospatial database management (PostGIS, Esri ArcGIS Server)
- · Analytical techniques using geostatistics and image processing techniques (ENVI, Earth Engine)
- · Expert mapmaking skills using desktop platforms (ArcMap, QGIS) and Mapbox Studio
- · Familiarity with collaborative software engineering and version control systems (Git/GitHub, SVN)
- · Experienced GIS software trainer and MissingMaps mapathon facilitator
- · Strong written and oral communication skills

#### CONTRIBUTOR TO PUBLICATION

International Union for Conservation of Nature Species Survival Commission (IUCN/SSC) Primate Specialist Group & Institut Congolais pour la Conservation de la Nature (ICCN). 2012. Bonobo (Pan paniscus): Conservation Strategy 2012–2022. Gland, Switzerland: p.65

Hickey, J., J. Nackoney, N. Nibbelink, S. Blake, A. Bonyenge, S. Coxe, J. Dupain, M. Emetshu, T. Furuichi, F. Grossman, P. Guislain, J. Hart, C. Hashimoto, B. Ikembelo, O. Ilambu, B. Inogwabini, I. Liengola, A. Lokasola, A. Lushimba, F. Maisels, **J. Masselink**, et al. 2013. Human proximity and habitat fragmentation are key drivers of the rangewide bonobo distribution. Biodiversity and Conservation. Vol. 22, Issue 13, p.3085-3104.

#### ADVISORY BOARD MEMBERSHIP / VOLUNTEERING

TusubiraTreasurer & Board memberSeattle, WA; 2014 – presentUshahidi deploymentTechnical support to activistsSeattle, WA; 2017 – present

Water supply engineering GIS support Uganda, 2005

# PROFESSIONAL ASSOCIATION MEMBERSHIP

- · Global Washington Ambassador
- OpenStreetMap US and OpenStreetMap Foundation
- · Society for Conservation GIS

## GEOGRAPHIC EXPERIENCE

· United States, Democratic Republic of Congo, Uganda, Philippines

## **LANGUAGES**

- French proficiency
- · Basic Luganda, Spanish, and Swahili